Hey, it's six o'clock, so we're going to
go ahead and get started. Uh, we'll
start with a roll call. Gary Sims, I
He's not here, and I do believe he is
still kind of on a sbatical. Uh, Josh
Chrysler
>> here.
>> David Benner
>> here. Elizabeth Decraer
Shner. Oh, okay.
I'm back. Patrick Butos
>> here.
>> Kelly Seir
>> here. Patrick Bon
>> here.
>> Check Berdick
>> Hey, we have a quorum. So, I'm going go
and get started. And then we have a new
member. Is she joining us? Is she
online?
>> Do you want to go ahead and introduce
yourself?
Yeah. Can you guys hear me? Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Perfect. Yeah. I apologize for not being
there. I'm in Casper at a training. So,
thank you for the Zoom link. Um, I'm
Josephine Carlson. I'm really excited to
be on the board. Um, looking forward to
the projects, even what we're going over
today. And I don't know what else you'd
like to know.
Um I think some of you if if you've been
on the board for a little while um we
gave her the Dubo award last year um for
the work that she did on her on her
home. So yeah. Well, welcome and
hopefully we'll see you in person next
time. Excited that you at least were
able to join us online tonight. Um,
so next item on the agenda is approve
approval of the minutes for the April
14th meeting.
Chair, I also just want to let you know
that Elizabeth is online now.
>> Oh, okay. Great.
Would anyone like to make a motion?
>> I'd move to approve the April 14
minutes.
>> I second the motion.
>> Is there any discussion?
No. All in favor say I. I.
>> I.
>> Any oppose? Same sign.
Hey. Are there any disclosures,
conflicts of interest? Does anyone need
to disclose at this time? No.
Audience business comments from the
audience.
I'm not usually down here, [laughter]
but uh thank you, Madam Chairman, and
members of the board. Uh this is a
really, really special historic
preservation month because we're
celebrating Cheyenne's greatest historic
preservation uh effort over at the pump
house. it is uh being a native and uh
having seen too many uh buildings
destroyed
and knowing uh the effort that goes into
uh saving something and really it was a
I think it's a compliment and an
important compliment to the people that
preceded you on this board because they
consistently over the years beginning
with the initiation of the board of
course really worked to raise that
consciousness to make those awards.
But [clears throat] it really wasn't
that the city of Cheyenne itself took
that leadership role until now. It was
uh really quite significant that a uh
pretty rough looking pump house uh got
the attention it deserved. And so that's
uh quite quite a statement. it is uh now
under uh analysis and I was talking to
uh the individual responsible
and he said he expects to see it uh
completed this year and so that's and
what's really important there is that
the funds will be available. It's uh
really wonderful to know that uh the
community is behind it. There was uh
some other council members that didn't
think it was such a hot idea, but really
it was the tour that we organized with
the uh alliance that really showed
people themselves because it excuse me,
it was a tucked away uh situation. So,
uh, I also noted when I looked up a
little bit of, uh, information before I
came down here that this is the 50-y
year anniversary of the historic tax
credits. And so that's uh I think we all
uh need to kind of
give a mental thank you to our
forefathers and foremothers and people
who really cared about our incredible
architectural heritage here in Cheyenne.
And that's uh pretty exciting to really
have seen it come to fruition. Uh, I
hope we can uh get some folks down there
pretty soon and take a look at what's
planned. It's not going to be a office
building. It's going to be a work work
building. And so that's uh really
meaningful. I just uh you can tell how
excited I am. It was uh something that
was that close.
That close. there was uh on the council,
you know, there's 10 of us and so I
would say it was about five to five and
so it was that it was the people coming
forward that really made the difference.
And so, um, I'm just, uh, believing that
it's going to be an example. And it's
not only that an example, it's part of a
much larger program that, uh, we are
seeing some great success on, two blocks
away from here along the Reed Avenue
corridor, those warehouses, the grain
elevator. I mean, there's some really
And I'm not sure what uh Tony's going to
do with ANC feed, but he's got some
unusual buildings there that could do
some unique things. So, this is a really
a big moment. We got $5 million for that
to fund the project after
almost 10 years of effort.
So, um, I'd like to hand out some
invitations if I could, Madame Chair.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Um, we're going to have a little party
over there on Thursday.
>> Oh, nice.
>> And, uh,
it's going to be
fun to take a look at
take a look at what we can accomplish.
because there's a number of
warehouses that
need some help. And of course, it's
always uh interesting to see that uh
when not only is uh it
Yeah,
>> the existing building. It is the
interest of the property owners and the
investors.
>> They're seeing the value of story
preservation.
So, uh, this is a big moment, a big day,
and a big month.
>> And this isn't all the good news. Um,
I think we're all somewhat aware of
what's happening down at the Hines
building in the hole. They haven't
finalized everything yet. And uh, but
after uh, 35 years of that I was
involved in it. Um, and I'm I don't know
if all [snorts] of you have been
upstairs in the Hines building because
it is unique and spectacular. And so
we're going to be having tours and
having showing people what's there
because it was state-of-the-art and has
stood the test of time. And we're going
to actually fill the hole, which is a
big big deal. And I was just over at uh
the Atlas Theater across the street and
what they're doing. So um there's a lot
going on. Oh, that's Yep. [laughter]
And and it it it comes from the heart,
does it not? It is uh it doesn't uh it
isn't just
um
another strip mall. It is it is uh has
has meaning. And I really uh just wanted
to come down today tonight and uh invite
you and point out what we've
accomplished together and what the
challenges are going to continue to be
because
we're getting older, the buildings are
getting older, and uh it's just
important that we uh make sure we do
what we can. and uh the corridor itself
15th Street down to the pump house
really really a big major project that
we've been working on a long time. We
just acquired some property down there
that's going to bring the greenway path
up. So it's uh we're building on what
was uh initially conceived of and that's
uh pretty darn exciting. So I really
appreciate your time. You got any
questions?
This is awesome. I'm so glad to see that
the Reed a Avenue corridor is happening
and that's awesome that there's a
celebration on Thursday. Appreciate you
inviting us. I mean, all of this is
really exciting. The Hines, the pump
house, and it's a pretty successful year
so far. So, [clears throat] thank you
for sharing.
>> I think I think we're going to be able
to make some hay out of it and say,
"Hey, we weren't so crazy, were we? This
was this had value and we we showed the
community that it did." and the
community responded and and really uh
with the pump house itself, that's a
city building.
That is not uh that's not private and
it's not uh it's it was really rough
looking, but uh we it's been extensively
analyzed. It's quite stout and and it's
going to going to go on and uh it's also
going to be part of other efforts in the
area. So, uh, all kinds of good in the
historic preservation month and the
historic preservation world and, uh,
hope you can come to our party.
>> Thank you. Does anyone have any
questions for Pete?
>> I don't have a question. I have I have a
comment.
>> Okay.
>> Um, Pete, I want to thank you for your
um, steadfast
work on this pump house. I I've only
been on the board for three years three
and a half years now, but this was a
topic of of concern for this board for a
long time and we've had a lot of
interaction with the city. And Pete, I
remember you coming and saying, "I'm
going to stand in front of the
bulldozer." Well, we didn't have to
>> and we and we're glad we didn't have to,
but your willingness to to stand up and
work with this board and and work with
people that needed to hear that the pump
house was important. And so, Pete, I
just want to uh you know, thank you for
your steadfast, you know, insistence
about, you know, working with this board
and and working to preserve the pump
house. It it really is a true victory
for the city, this board, and this whole
community that we were able together to
save the pump house. It it's really an
accomplishment that we uh should be very
proud of. And so was as we serving on
the council and sitting up there through
many experiences and lately they've been
pretty ugly experiences, but uh I was
appointed to be the champion of the pump
house.
uh they didn't think I was going to be
able to do it and uh a champion insists
and uh so we're we're very pleased and
we look forward to uh further
improvements and and really when you
look at our downtown um there have been
some
not too noticeable but very important
buildings that have been saved is a
couple little ones. I mean, what we're
seeing now is instead of a getting five
parking spaces, the building st is
staying up and people are uh committing
to it. So, it uh I also my office is at
1721 Warren in one of the oldest
buildings downtown, 1881.
And so, uh it it it it makes sense
financially as well as emotionally. and
I really appreciate uh appreciate your
time and look forward to uh our
continued efforts.
>> Thank you. Thank you so much.
>> Uh do we have any other audience
business?
Nope. Okay. Uh comments from city
council which I know Ken is not here.
Are you going to just speak on his
behalf? Okay.
>> Chair of the board. Charles Bloom
playing development director. Councilman
basketball asked me just to film and
briefly on what was going on at the
council level. For those of you who do
not watch the Monday night live event on
Zoom or YouTube or Facebook, um it's
been entertaining recently. Um there's
been a lot of public comment that is
lack of a better term AI driven. So
we'll just leave that there. Um, but the
high level items that they're they've
considered is they are issuing a new
micro brewery per micro brewery permit
for a new micro brewery that will be
located next to the Durbar at Cheyenne
Plaza. I know that is not necessarily
historic, but that complex is
approaching historic eligibility just
based on its age. Um, so look for that
um next to the Durbar. Um, that's been a
long uh time uh coming. It's been a
process. They've gone through our
department for a little while, but
they're taking their time, which is
great. Um, there were a lot of uh
different amendments uh and ordinances
that were approved. One of those was a
planting and development ordinance
amendment for Sweet Grass uh just to
change the uh size of a public park area
in the future, which would allow for
them to continue to move forward with a
potential private park facility that
would be privately funded. So, we'll see
if that um comes to fruition. Uh there
were some ordinances that were um
introduced. Um one of those um is
regarding reszoning of the HR Ranch PUB,
a portion of it. If you are out on
Industrial Road out to the east of town,
you see that neighborhood that's just
out in the middle of nowhere. There's a
whole other half that's been built with
alleys and roadways, small lots, garage
facing, kind of your historic type
design that you would see in the in the
old days. um that hadn't been developed.
They are actually looking to develop it
in that same pattern but with more
water-wise landscaping. So, they're
removing themselves from the PUB because
it has very strict uh sod and living
material requirements. So, that is
moving forward.
One of the more attention-grabbing items
that popped up was the introduction and
referral to committee of an ordinance
that would establish a moratorum on data
center development and massive
expansions for existing one. Uh that is
one that has echoed a lot of concern in
the industry lately as we've had a lot
of uh folks with their target on
Cheyenne. Um and there is a lot of
misinformation that is out there
surprisingly
uh using data centers and such to
generate the misinformation.
Um the facts of the data centers here in
the Cheyenne area are we mandate closed
loop systems. So your typical new large
data center you see like a a Walmart
sized one that's only using the
equivalent of about 3 to five single
family homes water per year. It's it's
very little water that is used to
facilitate the data centers. There are
ones that have high water use, but those
are ones that we do not see nowadays. We
have seen some in the past here before.
Uh golf courses are bigger water users,
car washes, those types of items. Uh
some single family homes are larger uh
users than our data centers that we have
today. Um the other uh discussion that
seems to be out there is
uh that the electrical rates are going
to go up for all of the taxpayers. Uh
Wyoming um Cheyenne and Black Hills
Energy worked together um a lot in the
past to create what is effectively
called tolling. Basically any large
energy uh user is required to
essentially foot the bill for the
generation, creation, distribution and
the the network to get the power from
where they're getting it um and how
they're getting it to their facility. So
basically they are required to offset
any additional cost. We were a model
state that many states have followed
since. A lot of the rhetoric you see
online is past practices that are
limited to a very small handful of
states nowadays. But again, it's just
misinformation that's out there. It's
there's a lot of information that that
does flow. Other concerns that have been
identified with data centers are what
are what happens for reuse in the future
uh when they are phased out in 30 years.
That's a question if you look around at
anything you see that's developed today.
What happens in 30 years? most places
that you look at, stores you shopped at
30 years ago, are they still here today?
A lot of them have changed names,
they've been repurposed, they've turned
into different things. Um, so there's a
discussion point about what about data
centers? What do we do? Um, so we'll see
how that that goes. that is sponsored by
one council member and we'll see if
there is additional support. But it
definitely has um echoed some uh concern
uh not only with data center developers
but with uh groups that have already
began to invest and are pretty far down
the line. But most importantly, uh, the
private residents of Laramie County and
of the city of Cheyenne that have, um,
exercised that they want to have the
freedom and the ability to sell and
market their property as they desire
instead of as a select few people
desire. So, that's moving forward um,
through our governing body. We'll see
what happens at public services and it
moves uh, forward through the governing
body. The other thing, the council is
busy with noon time work sessions. So,
if you want to hear how the city is
funded and how the $84 million budget is
distributed, um, tune in to this room
through your choice of of, uh, social
media platform or YouTube and you can
watch our budget presentations. Our
planning and development department
budget will be presented at noon on
Friday. Um, there are no surprises.
We're maintaining the status quo and
actually only um, asking for one light
line item to be increased to pay for a
little bit of overtime. Um, but we're
giving back money to the city between
about it's about
70,000 somewhere in there. It's a good
chunk of change because we had a
one-time fund for the comprehensive plan
which we are rolling over to this next
fiscal year. So, that's it for uh
council updates. If you have any
questions, I could probably answer them.
I spend most Monday nights here for
those council meetings. Um, but we can
also reach out to Councilman Asabel.
>> Does anyone have any questions?
Um, the next item is the report from
planning and development. I know you
probably did some of that. I don't know
if you have any other items to add.
>> Chair, members of the preservation
board, the only updates I have there
really are in regards to our
comprehensive plan. We have an RFP that
is presently out for solicitation.
basically asking firms to propose um
drafting a full revision of our
community character element of our
comprehensive plan. That's a lot of
words. I'm going to expect all of you to
know what it is. So I give a brief
overview. That is basically our land use
plan. So what is going to go where in
the future? It helps guide us in our
decisions when we reszone properties.
It's our broad overreaching policies and
principles regarding such topics as I'll
say it sustainability. Um equity is
another item sometimes uh there historic
preservation is a is an item. Um also uh
transportation planning, transportation
alternatives, all of those items that
help uh make your community a better,
more vibrant community. Those are all
topics that are to be discussed. Um the
one thing we also are looking at with
this comprehensive plan update is we're
asking all the consultants who respond
to provide an additive so an add-on to
the comp plan that would look at uh
commuting patterns in the region.
Specifically we're trying to identify
and update our numbers as to where
people are coming to work here. Um, back
in 2017, the last study was done and it
showed approximately 3,200 or so people,
maybe a little bit more coming in from
Larur County and Weld County to work.
Um, it had a inflow. There was a little
bit of outflow and there was a pretty
good inflow from uh, Albany County,
Wyoming and there was an outlier from
Sweetwater County that made no sense.
But anyway, that was there. Um, but
we're looking to get that updated to see
how things have changed, especially with
the uh boom in construction that we see
more recently to identify where those
folks are coming from. So, that's one of
the big issu items with the
comprehensive plan that uh period to
respond to the RFP that closes on May
28th. We hope to have a consultant on
board um and ready um for July 1st of
this year. Um other items um we
are working on two ordinances that are
moving forward to the planning
commission. One of those is regarding
historic horse racing. Right now a
majority of those establishments go to
the board of adjustment for review and
approval. I mean that's the biome
decision-making body. Uh a majority of
these are going to uh be required to go
to the governing body for review and
approval. This is supposed to coincide
with the statutory changes that were
made to give the cities more control
over the licensing of those facilities
as well. Another item that we have
moving forward is an amendment to
reclassify carports that are of certain
size and certain design um to allow them
to be uh constructed in front yards and
driveways and such. Um, as you may
notice when you drive around different
areas of town, 22nd Street is one that
just pops up right now. There's a couple
of car ports that are located above
driveways. Presently, none of those are
legal. If you see a carport in the front
yard of someone's house, there's a high
probability that it was not permitted
and is not an approved structure. Um,
this is a council member-driven um
amendment. We'll we'll see how it goes,
but we're going to take it forward
um for consideration. Um the highlights
of this um ordinance, the way we drafted
it is you
we looked at this three or four years
ago and when we did that, we looked at
requiring architectural compatibility.
It's hard to find that at a reasonable
price at Menard's. Um because most
people just look at the checkbook and
they look at the the price tag and they
say, "Oh, there's nice metal one with a
curve top." And that's what they end up
purchasing. Um so we're allowing those,
but we have a requirement that the lower
50% of any part of that structure cannot
be covered with metal sighting. So it
keeps it open. Um and it also uh limits
the desire for people to
put things there, lean things against
walls, start to acrewue stuff. So um
there are provisions that allow people
if they want to do something that
matches the house to fill them in
completely or more than 50%. Um so
you're rewarded for good design.
So that's I believe it from our
department that's high level unless
Aaron has anything to add.
Does anyone have any questions? Oh,
>> question. The illegal existing carports,
are you going to make them come up to
code for the new things or just leave
them in there? Because I I know there's
two of them on uh my street. So,
[laughter]
chair, members of the board, that's we
could spend all day um going through
zoning enforcement if we wanted to and
we could commit to being those those
folks in the community. We operate on a
complaint basis. Uh so if someone does
complain, that's when we start to
investigate. We do walk around a lot
with blinders on uh just because it's
it's painful sometimes to see what's
going on.
And
if if it's not complaint based, if it's
something that is blatantly illegal or
completely against uh an approved plan
that was recently approved, those are
times when we step up for an enforcement
action
because seems like it's a lot of a lot
of the 1950s and60s houses only had
single car garages and where they're
putting these things in is where they
have a single car garage and then
they're extending it so they can have
two cars. out of the hail.
>> Um, yeah, I just had a question. Um, Mr.
Leburn was mentioning like the hole in
the hines. Um, and I I was just curious
if there's like um is it accessible for
us to view the like the current plans
for what that looks like? Is that
something we can find online? Um, I'm
just thinking about I'm, you know, we
talk about the Hines all the time, but
curious about the um, and of course it's
listed on the National Register. So, I'm
just curious what the what the plans are
for, you know, you mentioning the upper
upper floors and if there's anything
related to historic preservation we need
to have our eye on as they're working on
that project that would affect the
historic integrity. Chair, members of
the board, um board member Chrysler,
that's a a really good uh question and
request. We have not seen any plans for
that that have been submitted. Um we've
just been
told that there will be housing units
and they will be building the structure
next to it. We haven't seen the actual
plans. Nothing has been submitted. Um I
do know the property owner is
very open to tours. They've given tours
of that facility before. So, if that's
something you all would desire, I think
that we could work on getting that put
together. As soon as we do have any
plans, that is something we will
definitely um share with historic
preservation board.
>> Yeah, I think at tours would be great.
Um and then also it just it sort of
connects into like the design guidelines
for downtown that we're sort of trying
to figure out how to move forward. So
especially for whatever they end up
putting into the hole, um it would be
good for us to have some sort of input
or eyes on that. So
>> yeah, chair three to the board. It's my
understanding that it will be a um it
will have parking on the rear portion of
it. It'll have some element of parking.
Um and then the Lincoln Way facing side
will have a storefront, at least on the
first floor. So you'll have an active
pedestrian space. That's the that's
what's been relayed to us so far, but we
haven't seen anything um that's been
designed nor anything that's been backed
by a pro-forma that um says that it can
actually fund itself. Um this is in a
tax increment financing urban renewal
plan and project area. So when square
footage is increased and added to the
area or when um property existing square
footage is enhanced and the value goes
up, it will generate a tax increment
that will um be eligible uh for use of
public you know of dollars for public
facing elements. One item that's been
highly um discussed as and being
eligible for tax increment financing
would be for facade uh repair and
renovation the existing structure and
facade enhancements to the new
structure. So regardless when this they
will be wanting to access that funding
because only those two lots can access
that funding. are the only eligible
folks. Um there will be a public review
process that surrounds that and we'll
definitely keep you all in the loop.
Yeah, that'd be great because I mean
when you're talking about parking um I
mean you're you're saying alley access
to well in a garage I guess I don't I
haven't looked at that so I don't know
if that's feasible for in and out and
turning radius and all of that but I do
think that the Bell building is a good
example of there being a entrance from
the street into the building and if
they're approaching it that way or if
that's too close to the intersection. So
yeah, be I'm very interested in in how
they're going to approach that and
hopefully do something that complements
the two buildings next to it.
>> Patrick,
>> I have a couple questions. Charles,
first is um I received a message from
the Shipo about a conference in
September. Um, and I'm not sure uh if
that's happening and and my question is
what's our training budget look like if
we wanted to send board members to that?
I think it's going to be in Casper if
I'm correct.
>> Yep, that's correct.
>> And I don't know if you guys talked
about it last
last month, but um I'm just putting on
the radar that, you know, we should
participate somehow. And Charles, I just
curious, you know, did we spend all our
money in in Denver and and is there
money to send, you know, probably the
the newest board members to that?
And, you know, I I don't know if it's a
two-day or
um
so Charles, it's just something to to to
look at. Um
and do you want to respond or just go?
You can come back next month and that's
fine. chair and members of the board, we
do have funding for travel. Um we
actually have a healthy travel allowance
um that's in the department that we've
uh dipped into for like planning
commissioner training and stuff um in
the past and we could always um leverage
that with um
some of the the board's funds if
desired. Um this year we have not uh
spent even
we still have extra in our travel
budget. notably because the travel a lot
of the travel that I have done um
is with National APA, that's American
Planning Association, and it's been
budgeted through grant awards. So, I've
been able to travel for next to nothing
on the city's dime. And then a lot of
our staff members don't seem to want to
get out of town too much. [laughter]
No, but um yeah, so we'll we'll see
where we are, but we could definitely
manage to to to explore that. Um
basically what we'd look at is
identifying what the registration is and
on what the
um the PDM and the hotels would be in
mileage.
>> Josh,
>> um my my understanding too is that the
shipo is providing
funding for up to three people from each
CLG to attend. That's what I understood
from the email that the shipo would be
providing some pro. Yeah, that's
probably true.
>> Yeah, I think I think the registration
fees were waved if you were with a seal.
>> So, we sent everybody. [laughter]
Um, second question, Charles, is uh I
know that the board has recently spent
some money. I think we put a line item
in for $7,000
for the fountain for an assessment. And
I know uh I think we've I don't know um
Gary gave us some money for uh ornaments
and that kind of stuff. And uh if at
next month's meeting you could just tell
us where we are financially. I I you
know I just curious um with that $7,000
commitment like what are we looking at?
Um, and then
the last thing is at the retreat,
Charles, you mentioned that you had um
contacted the
school board and somebody in the
Brownfields program concerning uh Heert
Elementary and I'm wanting to know if
there's any progress on that. and and
Charles, the other thing is I'm
personally interested in in working with
whoever we need to work with at the
school district and uh at EPA. Um, I
used to work at EPA, so there may be a
little bit of issue with my conflict of
interest, but [laughter]
um, I'm interested in in that project
and if there's any been any movement on
that and if there's anything that I can
do from my perspective. Charles,
>> chair, 32 to um, the commission and
commissioner. U, um, I can answer the
question about the funding. Right now,
we do get our report from the finance
department. Right now there's uh
$32,2461
that are unrestricted 1 cent that is uh
through revenue from the ornament sales
those items there is $155,7326
as restricted which is the um
restriction from the will uh for the
historic um fountain. So that's
>> thank you. That's that. Um, regarding
the EPA assessment grant award, um, I
was just talking to our environmental
consultant on Monday or Friday. I don't
know what day it was. It was either
yesterday or Friday, um, about this. The
EPA generally contacts folks in miday to
identify if they were a recipient of
that award. And if we are recipient of
the award, then we go out to RFP where
we solicit someone to um basically go
through the Brown Fields assessment
program. It's a half million dollar uh
award is what it is. Um and then we
would be able to get those folks on
board. Um and then the eligibility spend
would begin federal fiscal year on
October 1st. So that's when we would
have that. But we're keeping our fingers
crossed that we'll get the award um in
the next couple of weeks. At least the
announcement and a press release will go
out. Um we didn't get the last one um
but we think we're very optimistic on
this one.
>> Thank you, Charles.
>> Any other questions?
>> All right, we'll move on to strategic
goals reports. Oh,
>> I'm sorry, chair. ment I had mentioned
or my item if there's any way we could
modify the agenda possibly to take yes
>> the new business before the update
session I think our
>> visitors would appreciate that
>> yes absolutely um okay so for new
business we have a certificate of
appropriateness um this is for uh 418
West 1st Avenue um this was the project
we discussed in last month's meeting
is there a presentation that Oh Okay. Or
I guess Charles, do you have No. Okay.
Would you like to come up and to talk
about your project? I think we've kind
of got a general idea of what you're
doing, but if you want to just give a
brief overview.
>> I can also give the staff report first.
>> Oh, sure.
>> And then and then you can go after.
>> Okay.
>> Um, so this is a demolition permit and
certificate appropriateness to allow an
attached garage to be demolished and a
new addition built. The property is
located within the More Haven Heights
Historic District and is zoned to MR
Medium Density Residential. The property
is located at 418 West 1st Avenue and is
legally described as lot 15, block 35,
More Haven Heights. The property is
north of West 1st Avenue between Bent
and Pioneer Avenues. The property is
surrounded by the MR zone on all sides.
There is an existing residence with an
attached garage on the property. The
residence was built in 1935 and is a
one-story side gabled brick residence
that represents the tutor architectural
style. The exterior walls of the
building consist of a tan brick laid in
a stretcher bond pattern with dark brick
window sills. There's an attached hipped
roofed onecar brick garage on the north
side of the dwelling. In 2007, the
residence was listed as good physical
integrity and good integrity of setting.
The structures listed as a three
contributing status. The owner seeks to
obtain a demolition permit and a
certificate of appropriateness to
demolish the attached garage and
construct a new addition. The garage is
deteriorating and is causing a safety
concern. The garage is unusable and the
garage would be accessed by the alley
and is not visible on First Avenue. The
changes that the applicant has proposed
primarily affect the rear of the
residence. The existing attached garage
has been damaged and has structural
failure. There have been separation of
layers within the brick face. The brick
face has pitched away from this um
substructure and has cracked and bowed
in multiple locations causing a
potential collapse of the eastern face.
The affected loose areas um were removed
for safety reasons. There has also been
cracking to the interior masonary of the
western wall of the garage requiring
temporary interior reinforcements being
installed to prevent an uncontrolled
collapse. Both wooden doors entry and
overhead are decayed.
Staff has reviewed the proposal and
determined that it meets the criteria
for the following reasons. Number one,
the requested demolition is limited to a
deteriorated rear garage that has
experienced structural failure and
presents a safety concern. The structure
is not visible from the public rightway
and its removal will not significantly
impact the historic character of the
primary residence for the Mor Haven
Heights Historic District.
Um the proposed addition number two, the
proposed addition generally maintains
the existing footprint and is designed
to be compatible with the primary
structure and scale massing and roof
form. The project is consistent with
surrounding uses and zoning
requirements. It does not create adverse
impacts to public health, safety, or
general welfare. Due to meeting all the
review criteria, staff recommends
approval of the demolition permit and
the certificate of appropriateness.
>> Oh, thanks.
>> Want to introduce yourself and
>> Good evening. I'm Chris Merithu. M I
T-W. Uh we moved Cheyenne a little over
a year ago. love the place and we're
trying to make it more of a home.
>> Anything to add on the addition that
you're putting?
>> No, I think everything was pretty much
in the report you saw that yes, the
current garage not only is coming down,
but our car won't even fit in it. It's
obviously built for 1935 Model T, so
it's totally worthless. And I've removed
what things I was concerned about. So
that's the point we're at is the other
issue is for today's lifestyles, the
house really isn't functional for a lot
of people. It's a one-story, onebedroom
upstairs with three bedrooms and one
bathroom downstairs. So anybody who has
toddlers, children, etc. would not find
it really much of an acceptable home.
We're both the youngest in our families
and we're both past 70. So any family
members that come to visit us, we have
the issue of getting down the old
basement stairs. You know what 1935
stairs are like. Yeah. So that's why
we're looking to make some improvements
and bring it up to today's needs.
>> Does anyone have any questions?
No. Would anyone like to Oh, go ahead. I
just had had one question for you about
um that I couldn't tell from the report
and it looked like from the staff report
they weren't sure either what materials
you're planning to use for the facade of
the addition
>> problem.
That's the current brick that's on it.
>> Mhm.
>> Which we can't find.
Nobody seems to even close to it
anymore. So, what we're looking at doing
is a board and batten siding on the back
in that color to blend it in as best we
we can to
the board and bat would be appropriate
for the age. And then the color just
trying to get as close to the the brick
color as we can. Well, and I think it is
good to differentiate between the
historic and and the new structure. So,
>> we can't hide it as a new structure. So,
>> y
>> make it smooth it in.
>> And then just to follow up on that, did
I understand also that you used some of
the historic brick off the garage to
repair the chimney to
>> several places on the front and the top
third of the chimney had to be rebuilt.
So again, we were faced with brick. So
we
the ones that we were able to salvage
that weren't busted up, that's what we
used them for.
>> Yeah, I think that's great. You're able
to reuse that material. And
>> yeah,
>> this isn't our first historic. The 1860,
I think, was the last one we worked on.
So yeah, we've we've been through the
process. We understand.
>> Yeah, it was pre-Ivil War. So
yeah.
The house sat on four granite boulders
on the corners. We started with
foundation up. So, yeah, we've we've
been through this.
>> Any other questions?
Nope. Okay. You look like you wanted to
press the button. So,
>> I don't have questions, but I do have
some some issues and I don't know.
>> Yeah, I think we might want to start
with a motion and and then discussion. I
would move to approve the demolition
permit.
>> Anyone?
>> Anyone want a second?
>> I have a question on the motion.
>> Is the mot are we considering just the
demolition or demolition and
construction?
>> Demolition and construction.
>> I would second the motion to approve the
certificate of appropriateness.
discussion.
Patrick, you want to you have comments,
questions?
>> Several. Um, first um I want to kind of
I think um
this concerns me for for a couple of
reasons. one is um I I know it's it's
it's it's in the back, but um I I'm
going to take issue with uh the staff's
recommendation number two that this
generally maintains the existing
footprint. The existing footprint
is being doubled.
That's not in the it's not the same
footprint. You're what you're doing is
you're taking
about a 12 by I don't know what is it 18
>> 12 x 20
>> 12 by 20 and going to a uh what is it 20
>> 23
>> 27 by 29
>> which is double
and you know I understand this is 1935
but what you're doing is basically if
you look I'm glad you have this photo up
there or this rendering
is basically you're doubling the size of
the back of the house,
>> right?
>> Um that really changes for me the whole
character of the particular house
because
um I I know you it's not visible from
the street. I know you have issues with
garages. I have a small garage, too. I
can't fit my car in it. Um, so, um, a
and I have no issues with taking down
the garage, but you're, my first issue
is that you're doubling the size, and
that changes for me the whole character
of the back of the house in relationship
to the front of the house. Now, I get
the point that it's not visible, but it
changes the whole character of the house
for me. It makes it twice as large as it
is right now. So, um I mean I
you you really are substantially
changing the footprint and that's my my
first concern. Um
the other concern is that um Josh kind
of alluded to it and that's materials.
It makes me a little bit uncomfortable
to demolish and put something up without
adequate
information for me. I'm not sure I mean,
there's a there's a reference to windows
in here. I don't know what the material
what the the the the makeup of those
windows are going to be. Are they going
to be consistent with the with the rest
of the house? Um, you know, you you
talked about lap siding. I don't know if
any of the roofing materials, any of the
other features are going to be cons
compatible, but not the same as the
front of the house. I understand that
concept, but I I feel like I'm operating
with a little bit of of information and
not enough and kind of taking it on
faith that you're going to um you know,
provide something that's that's not
going to be an isore and that's going to
be, you know, compatible with the other
structures in the neighborhood and and
compatible with the the the front of the
house. So that I I I just feel like
there's not enough information
um in terms of what goes I feel
comfortable what comes down but I'm not
comfortable with what goes in that those
are kind of my my issues uh my two
issues is that the the increase in the
footage you're doubling the size which
for me totally changes the character of
that particular
uh house as it stands.
and the other is the uh reconstruction.
I just don't feel like I have enough
information and um in terms of materials
that would be used and and uh how that
addition will be
um reconstructed
so to speak. Can I answer those
questions for him?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Uh the windows in the house were
replaced some time ago, a short time
ago. They're Sierra Pacific windows
which we were planning on matching uh
from Wyoming Building Supplies where
we're getting them from. Uh the roof
you're going to re-roof the whole house
and everything when we get the addition.
>> Are are they aluminum windows?
>> No. So they're final.
Glenda
>> Linda
>> but and the exterior is alumin
uh there's a picture in there of the
house as of last week or whatever that
shows the windows
show from the house current
>> y
>> front of the house
>> chair if I could get a moment to clarify
the scope of the application
when you're ready. So, you're looking at
the windows. That's something to say.
>> Sorry. You you're going to clarify the
scope of Is that what you said?
>> Okay.
>> Would do you mind just kind of repeating
that for record about the windows?
>> Uh the windows that are currently on the
house, which is pictured in the very
last picture,
those are bad aluminum with she worked
in the window business.
The windows are aluminum clad exterior,
clear pine interior,
so they're stainable to match the
existing woodwork, the original
woodwork, original doors and trim.
Yep.
>> The style of the windows is consistent
with the tutor revival architectural
style.
>> Thank you.
And Charles is gonna Oh, do you have a
comment?
>> Yes. Um, I'm I'm looking at the last two
pictures. And the first picture is the
front of the house, which are one over
ones.
And then the second page is, I'm
assuming, well, yeah, if that's the if
that's the back, those are what? Three
over3.
>> Those were the photos from the original
real estate listing from three years
ago. So those no longer exist. The three
over3
>> and and the replacements are the one
over one
>> on the front.
>> That I don't know what you're the
>> this this one right here. The one over
one.
>> No, this this is the correct photo.
>> You're looking at the the one
>> the one over one are originals. The
three over three are replacement. Am I
correct?
>> Yep.
>> That's the That's what it looks like
today.
>> That's what it looks like today.
>> And that's what you're proposing to put
>> in in the three window openings that are
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> And I think Charles wanted to clarify
the the scope.
>> Chair, members of the board, Charles Bo
playing director. Um I just want to note
we don't do these very often. This is in
a national registry store district and
it's labeled as a contributing
structure. So it triggered the review
under chapter 64 of title 2 2.64.
Um the basically what we're looking at
is uh one piece which is is it
appropriate to demolish the structure?
Um and the historic preservation board
can either say yes it is due the
structural failure or no it isn't. And
then they can also um approve the
demolition
with or without conditions.
[clears throat]
So with this specific application, it
was uh demonstrated they're demolishing
it. I mean because they are talking
about the structural um issues with the
property and they have um proposed this
additional structure that will replace
that. Um so it is within your purview to
condition it as you see fit for the
replacement. I just want to let you all
know that your primary
uh review element here is just the
demolition not the design of the
replacement structure if that makes
sense. And that's why I asked my
question, Charles, are we discussing
just demolition or demolition and
reconstruction? And now I'm and I was
told it was both. Now I'm hearing that
it's just demolition.
>> Chair three for clarification
>> with conditions. If we want to do it,
>> chair, that is correct. Because what
board member just said, it's demolition
with
conditions that could mitigate that
demolition which could be elements of
the design.
>> So is it in our purview to recommend
design
elements or or
I guess I'm
>> chairman
>> I'm still confused.
>> Chair, members of the board, you all are
the decision makers on this process. So
your decision that comes out of this
today is the final decision.
This any appeals of this would um be
appeals based on a decision being made
in clear error and they would go to the
um district court. So this is not a
review recommendation. This is a
decision
>> opportunity.
>> Understood. Yeah. And thank you for the
clarification because unfortunately I
assumed that it was more than the
demolition permit. So, that's good to
know. Um, did you have any further
comments? Cuz I have some comments to
make.
>> No, that
>> Okay. Um, I I do appreciate you guys
clarifying how you're going to replace
the re the roof um in its entirety. So,
everything is matching. Um, and the
clarification on the windows also
matching. The Hardy board to me seems
appropriate material. Um, it is
complimentary of what you have. Um, and
I know I'm speaking more on design,
Charles. Um, but I'm an architect, so
you'll have to forgive me. Um, but I
guess in in my opinion, I I don't know
if I would have any conditions to the
demolition. Um, I do understand that
they're increasing the size, but
numerous homes in this district have.
Um, as long as they're not
modifying the front facade that is
visible, um, I I guess I have less issue
with the the size that they are are
putting up. Um,
I guess in my opinion, I would not add
any additional conditions to the
demolition [clears throat] process. It
sounds like they have done this historic
preservation before and are
understanding and have clearly replaced
the windows that look a lot more
appropriate than what they had previous.
So that that's I guess my comment.
Anyone else?
No.
>> Um I do.
>> Okay.
Um, I was curious, what does the current
um car garage door look like? Is it a
sectional garage door? I didn't see it
on the pictures unless I'm missing it.
>> It's a wood structure with
squares, you would consider it, sections
of it. It's a rollup door.
>> Oh, okay. Yeah. I was curious if it was
kind of like a a carriage house type
style. Okay, thank you.
>> Just very plain door.
>> Yeah,
>> standard door.
>> It faces into the north, so it has taken
all of the weather for however many
years it's been up there.
>> Sure. All right. Thank you.
>> Is there any other comments before we
vote?
Okay. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> I. I.
All oppose. Same sign.
>> I
So motion passes.
>> Oh, I'm Yeah, sorry. I didn't I didn't
hear it. Was Elizabeth and
um Josephine? Did you Did you guys
>> It was Josephine. And yes, I I agree
with
the majority and I want to say welcome
to Cheyenne and thank you for your
mindful diligence on this project.
>> Thank you.
>> And Elizabeth, did you
>> Yeah,
>> we didn't hear.
>> You did. Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. So, we're going to move on to
strategic goals report, uh, National
Register of Historic Places.
>> Um, Elizabeth, it sounded like things
with the checks, um, are getting
uh, back on track. Is that correct?
>> Yes. So, this month really was mostly
admin.
Um, it was making sure that all the
invoices were correctly paid and I did
get paid. So that is exciting for
everyone. [laughter]
Um but yeah, so I feel like now we're
really ready to go and and dive into
this project now that that um previous
work has been compensated. So I'm
excited to get going on it.
Do you want to provide any updates on
the reports of
what you've been doing for the terminal
and
the other
>> Yeah.
>> This month hasn't been um a lot of
research or anything like that. Like I
said, it's been primarily just trying to
get the admin process taken care of um
so that way I know that I can move
forward um with those projects. So, I
was kind of just waiting to see how that
all shook out first. Um, and like I
said, ready to
get going. So, well, I'll have a a
better um research
uh updated report next month for sure.
>> Um, and Elizabeth, are you feeling like
you're on still on track to complete
both of them on time? I think it's I
can't remember what the deadline is.
September something. Yeah, I believe
it's November or something something
like that that
>> Yes. So,
>> September. Okay.
>> Yeah. So, for the National Register
nomination, it just needs to be a draft
according to the contract.
>> Okay.
>> So, I can get that to Casey for her
review. Um, and I believe it is stated
in that contract as well that um, even
outside of that September date, I will
still help with edits
um, to get the nomination ready to
submit. Um, so I feel pretty good about
that one, especially knowing that
[laughter] we'll have that that time to
get that going. Um, and I have been
finding, you know, the last couple of
months when I've been kind of plugging
on, there are some really great
resources for the African-American
context study, um, I have pulled
together quite a number of residences
and associated structures. What I'm
really finding is that not a lot of them
exist anymore because it was primarily
in the westside area that's been taken
over by industrial
um
companies and things of that nature. So,
um I think I found one or two that are
still standing, but they're historic
integrity is pretty low. Um
but yeah, so that's kind of
where that is. But
>> I do I do feel pretty confident on that.
Um and so I need to get into archives
and start start
uh going on it.
>> Does anyone have any questions for
Elizabeth?
>> No. Uh oral history projects.
>> I don't have a lot of updates. Um this
time at the last meeting um Amber had
gave me the contact information for
somebody that I should talk to about the
Hoffman building which is on um
uh 15th. Um we discovered it and I I
reached out to her uh twice and haven't
heard back so I don't think she's
probably interested. Um but that's all
that I um accomplished on on the oral
histories this month.
>> It's unfortunate. Now you have a new
lead with Aaron's dad. Uh [laughter]
I did some real
um so historic preservation month. Um we
did have the mayor's proclamation
yesterday. Um so thank you for those
that came. Um that was good recognition.
Um the deo award uh I that's going to
reopen on July 31st or
>> no chair through you. Um, I've been
working with Matt Murphy and he is has
reopened it. So, it is currently
reopened to July 31st. Um, he has told
me that he will put out a Facebook post
on the city page any day now. And then
so we'll be able to repost that one once
he gets that out there. Great.
Great. Um, and then the L. Clerk Jones
award. Uh we did determine a date to
give that award which will be June 6
from 12 to 3:00. Uh they are ex
extremely excited um to receive this
award. So they are making it quite a
large event. They plan on having food
and beverages, some specialty cocktails
from Chronicles Distillery and it'll
actually coincide with the summer nights
um I mean summer on the streets. Sorry,
wrong.
Um, no, sorry that that's where I got
confused. No, it's it's somewhere on the
streets and it's a I guess a getting to
know Cheyenne again. I'm not exactly
sure 100% what this event is, June.
>> Yeah, like a block party, I guess. So, I
I'm hoping to find out more on Thursday.
We do have a um steering committee uh
planning meeting on Thursday to uh meet
actually with the building owner and and
do some more planning for this event.
So, I'm I'm pretty excited about that.
So, um I guess David, do you have
anything else on Historic Preservation
Month that you can think of?
>> Uh no.
>> Okay. And chair, we'll also have a press
release going out about that pretty
soon. Perfect. Yes.
>> Will we have the plaque by then? Have we
can
>> I will call Trophy and see if they have
it done yet. I haven't heard back from
them. They It's
>> place. Oh, okay.
>> Yeah, it's ordered. They just haven't
let me know if it's ready yet or not.
>> It's one of the reasons why we wanted to
kind of push it to the June 6 is to make
sure we have the plaque in hand to give.
Um, and the weekend before is graduation
weekend and we assume that too many
folks will probably be a little bit
busy. So that's why it got pushed to
June. So it didn't meet historic
preservation month. But yeah,
>> um
>> at least the public are the
announcements going out this month. So
>> um just a question about the mayor's
proclamation yesterday. Is was like
those pictures shared that we can share
on our historic preservation board page
or anything like that?
>> Thank you for mentioning that. I did
have photos um taken on my phone. I
will. Elizabeth, can I send those to you
to put on Facebook?
>> Yes, that was on my list to ask for as
well. So, that would be perfect.
>> Okay,
I will. Yeah, I'll I'll get this sent to
you.
Um the I'm sure as you guys probably
know by now we are not doing a tour of
the pump house um in the month of May.
Uh I think with how the building has
moved forward and its progression they
don't see a point of doing a tour at
this point um there will be ri ribbon
cutings and those sort of things to
come. So, uh, the alliance is still
keeping it on their their watch list
and, um, but I I don't think we're going
to be doing any tours of the pump house
anytime soon. So, um, other than that, I
don't think we have anything else going
this year for historic preservation
month. You know, as David has kind of
mentioned before, we're going to try and
start planning for next year so we can
be on the ball and and have more things
going on for the month of May. Um, I
guess any questions or comments for
historic preservation month?
No. Uh, education of the public
and marketing.
>> I'm not sure about the marketing part,
but [laughter] uh I'm still trying to
track down the 1990 video that uh that
if I can find it. Can we put videos on
Facebook? I don't know about that. So,
if I can find that uh uh but uh it the
link got taken down or expired because
of old age or something. I don't know
how that all works, but uh I don't I
think there's one guy might have made a
copy of that onto a flash drive. So, I'm
going to see if I can track him down.
>> What was the What platform was the video
on?
>> It was on a flash drive [laughter] and
transferred to a flash drive and the
flash drive went on to a website and
when you click on that website link it
says expired.
>> It was not not on the city. It was on
some other thing that this art Bill
Lindstöm from the arts like the transfer
from VHS
to digital and he had loaded it on this
uh some website that you could link to,
but last time I linked to it, it just
said
this link is expired.
>> Glenn Garrett, that was the architect
that you were asking me about earlier.
And this was a video of what was a video
of
>> uh in 1990 the board of public utilities
paid to have a uh video of they did it
either 21 or 22 buildings went along
saying what kind of style they were.
Couple of them they actually went inside
and showed the inside of the buildings.
It was uh uh Bill Dubo was the guy that
spoke on the uh the whatever the
commentary or whatever you call it on
there. And uh it was sent out to all the
third grade classes in uh this school
district and one of the teachers had
retired and still had a copy of the VHS.
All the rest of them disappeared. the
city didn't have a copy of it that we
could find, but I got the tape from her
and got it transferred over to uh
digital, but uh I'm not sure. I might
have to go back to see if she still kept
the VHS. It's It's getting to the point
where trying to uh find a VHS player
[laughter]
to to And it was VHS quality. So, you're
talking like 240 or 200
uh pixels instead of this new for 4K and
1080 or whatever. So, when you show it
on a big
anything ba basically bigger than about
a 21 inch TV, it looks like a really
blurry mess. But but on a small
smaller than 21 in it actually it looks
pretty decent and it's got a lot of neat
information on it but and uh but we
talked about doing it but to redo it I
think would cost quite a bit. They got a
grant to do the thing back in 1990
and so
>> we'll turn on that old Commodore
computer. Um we use that for most our
staff reports anyway. We still have it
budget, you know, it's a bummer. So,
we'll see what we can find on those 5
and a/4 inch floppies hanging out.
We might we'll take a look and see what
we have in our our documents. We do have
a uh
we do have a backup system in our
clerk's office.
Maybe, just maybe,
something's out there.
Cautiously optimistic.
Any
anything else before we move to
Elizabeth?
Elizabeth, do you have any reports for
the marketing?
>> I do. Um though this last month period,
we shared um Shipo's preservation plan
um on our socials. We also did the
Carnegie Library, which got a lot of
attention online, so that was really
great to see. Um, and we also shared the
DDA banners project as well. Um, I still
want, as I just mentioned, wanted to do
the mayor's proclamation and share that
as well this week. Um, and then coming
up that I wanted to get some folks
thoughts on as well. Quite a few things
that have popped up. Um, on May 15th,
it's the first airline stewardist's
flights um, from 1930. So it was San
Francisco to Cheyenne and then Cheyenne
to Chicago. So that's one thing we could
do especially with the airport um
connection.
Uh on the 19th it is it was noted that
in 1920 the first congregational church
um had its steeple removed and I believe
that's on the south side. Um so that
might be a good tie into that historic
district. Um I don't believe it's there
anymore. when I did just a a quick
little five minute search. Um and then
of course the Dubo Award will advertise
that like I got permission for um a
couple board meetings ago.
Um June 5th is when the Masonic Temple
Cornerstone was laid in 1901, which I
think is a a definite post that we
should do. And then um on June 6th or
the 7th um if we have photos I'll do the
Lerk Jones Award um post as well. Or if
we want to do that earlier, we can do
that too. So that's kind of what I got.
That's awesome. I I think for the L
Clerk Jones award um was we're working
on doing a little bit of uh research for
the owner in order to kind of help tell
the story on June 6. And so maybe in
kind of promotion of the event, um I
know we have some historic photos, but
maybe we can share those with some of
that history beforehand. Um
yeah,
>> great. Yeah, just get me whatever you
got. We'll put it up.
>> Cool.
Any other comments for marketing
committee?
>> Those all sound like great ideas.
on ornaments. Gary is not here, so we'll
um I guess skip that one. Um airport
fountain planning, Kelly.
Yes. So um Pacific Coast Conservation
um is on site this week working on their
test fills and testing some different
materials. Amber and Patrick and I went
out and met with Lucinda today. Um she
arrived in town yesterday and will be
here till Friday morning. So um
basically what she explained to us after
she's done a little bit closer
investigation is that she it took her a
little while to figure out exactly what
was original glaze from the original
terracotta blocks versus what the the
patch and fill material that was used
previously like the epoxy from the
company that came in I think in 2020 and
did some fills to areas that had been
lost. Um, but once she pointed it out,
you can actually kind of see what's
original versus what was previously
filled. It's a little bit different in
color. So, that was interesting. Um, but
she said through looking at it closer as
well, she realized that the areas that
are failing and coming off are not all
necessarily just the epoxy that was put
on previously that's non-porous. Um, it
is there are several areas that look
like it's the original glaze that's
actually popping off.
Um, both of those are probably still
likely from water that's, you know,
intruding and seeping up into those
terracotta blocks and not able to
properly
evaporate or drain through like the
grout joints. Um,
so
she's going to continue. She said she's
got about like 10 different products
total. And she was kind of explaining to
us different combinations that she's
testing out and trying to figure out
what's going to work best, what's going
to stick to the exposed sort of raw
terracotta where those areas have flaked
and chipped off. Um, and what is going
to be permeable. I think she was one of
the tests she was working on is an
initial coat that takes like 48 hours to
cure. So, she was going to try to get
those done by the end of day today. And
then she's got another product, a glaze
product that she would go over it with
that's permeable and should allow
moisture to evaporate better than the
epoxy product or something similar that
would not be permeable.
Um, so the plan is still for her to
continue working this week, figure out
what she thinks going is going to work
best, and then we kind of just sit and
wait. And she's also going to document.
She was going to um take some time today
to number every block on the fountain on
the exterior wall and then the interior
pedestal since there's failures on both.
and she's going to mark out on a plan
like norththeast, southwest and have,
you know, specific designations for each
area of the wall so that we have really
clear documentation on exactly what's
there and what she's doing this week.
She said she's going to try to complete
fills on at least a couple or a few of
the blocks. So, we have like a good
example of kind of a finished area to
watch and monitor over the next year
when the fountain's running and then
through the fall and winter so it can go
through a freeze thaw cycle. And rather
than probably scheduling them to make
trips up to check progress, if we have
that documentation as a committee, we
can go out and review it periodically
throughout the year and just see what
happens and how well that fares. Um, the
other major thing that she
kind of reiterated and confirmed for us
that we've heard before is that it
doesn't make sense to put any more money
in the future into repairing the
fountain and the terracotta itself until
we address like the water intrusion and
the leaking that we know is happening.
Um, so next steps, we need to reach back
out to Jason Sanchez at the city and try
to set up a meeting um with them so that
we can get down in the vault below the
fountain before they fill it and start
operating it for the summer so we can
get a good idea of what it looks like in
there. There was one of the floor drains
in the fountain was completely backed
up. Um, there's like a puddle sitting in
there today, even in the heat and it's,
you know, pretty well dried out from the
storm last week. just completely like
clogged and not draining at all. So,
that is concerning. We know they said
they've had issues like keeping it clear
of leaves and feathers and whatever else
is clogging up the filter and making it
hard for the city to maintain that and
keep it running. Um, so we need to do
definitely a little bit more
investigation and talking to the city
and get some ideas on, you know,
plumbers that have worked on that
fountain in the past as well as if the
city has any ideas fountain specialists
because I think it might require that to
do some better investigation and
identify what actually is going on, if
it's like the cracking in the tile floor
that's allowing water to get in or or
what's happening. So,
got a little more work to do. Not a ton
of um progress as of today, but I do
think it's still positive that we've
got, you know, a professional and a
preservation expert out there kind of
reinforcing some of
the things that we've been talking
about. Oh, and I guess the the one other
major point she made today was that
after
realizing some of those things and that
it's not just the epoxy that's failing,
it's actually the original glaze. She
said it would not make sense. We had
talked about in their original proposal,
they said like option one is just sort
of spot treat and propose an ongoing
maintenance plan where they may need to
come up once a year and repair any
additional losses. that option two that
we had talked about would be like more
of a full epoxy removal and more
permanent repair. She said because the
original glaze is coming off just as
much as the epoxy is, that really
wouldn't be feasible because she said
like the mechanical removal takes a lot
of the original material and it just
doesn't make sense because it is the
original terracotta glazing that's also
failing.
So, their recommendation is still to to
monitor it, figure out how it fares and
what products work best, and then
discuss with the city an ongoing
maintenance plan and figure out how we
can
set aside some funds um whether that's
city funds and or
board funds or money from the the will
bequest. So, the challenge with that
obviously is it's going to cut back
quite a bit on the beautifification and
the other things we were hoping to do
with the park and the landscaping and
signage and all of that.
Yeah, I I think um like Kelly said,
we're going to plan to meet there and at
least just get a first glance at what's
going on and and understand some of that
water infiltration and that way we know
the appropriate next step as who we need
to contact. Um you know, Patrick's
already looked at the electrical and
that's a little bit of a mess. So, we
know we know we need to address that.
But before we address that, we have to
address the water issue. So, um, and
hopefully we we'll reach out to Jason
here in the next couple weeks because if
they intend to turn it on around
Memorial Day because that's usually the
plan, then we want to make sure we get
ahead of that. So, we are we get down
there and investigate prior, have them
turn the water on because we do actually
want it to go in there so we understand
what's happening when there is water.
Um, and then have another visit after
it's running for a little bit. So, yeah.
Yeah, like Kelly said, probably not
anything you guys wanted to hear, but
it's what it is. [laughter]
Um, I guess any questions for Kelly?
>> Just thank you for taking that on on
behalf of the rest of us because it
sounds very complex. So, [laughter]
>> um, the pump house, I think we've
already discussed enough. I don't know
if we need to make any further comments
on that. Uh, design guidelines. Um, we
have not met again since the last
meeting. Um, but I I think we need to
probably meet soon on that to continue
progressing that forward. So, um, well,
so no new updates on design guidelines.
Um,
and then I don't think anything else is
new with the watch list items.
So
>> I I have a comment on the watch list
items demo by neglect and it's only just
sort of a halfformed thought, but I
thought I would mention it for the board
to think about. I just, you know, we're
talking about like all the data centers
coming in and like, you know, sort of
the concern around the community about
everything going on with that. Um, which
I think a lot of has to do with like
concerns about it changing like the
character of Cheyenne. Um, which is
really closely connected to historic
preservation of course. Um,
and I don't know if that makes I don't
know if that makes any difference in
terms of like if we want to think about
timing of like trying to circle back to
demo by neglect if people are seems like
people are sort of all of a sudden
feeling more open to like regulations of
things. Um,
and I do I don't know. So, it's just a
halfformed thought that I thought I
would throw out there, but I don't know.
And there doesn't have to be any
response, but
>> I mean, the the the
um
let's see, was it the the ordinance is
already written, right?
So the I mean just the the the hard work
of the ordinance and you know we took a
lot of time to address a lot of concerns
that
at least some former council members
had. And so the it it's not an issue of
writing the ordinance. It's an issue of
timing, Josh, that, you know, this might
be a time to maybe test the waters
again. And I and I don't know how to go
about that, but um I
and I don't under, you know, maybe you
have a better pulse on the climate,
political climate. Uh you know, I I I I
don't know. Um, I mean, you know, if if
maybe we could talk with Pete. Pete
seems, you know, he's real happy about
the pump house and, you know, maybe
there's some some momentum there that we
might be able to take advantage of, but
I don't know enough about the sort of
where the council is.
I think right now it's you're starting
the election cycle. I think what like
the next couple days is when they start
uh the filing for the different offices
and stuff. So, I'm not sure whether
starting something during the middle of
uh campaign right now and we might have
changes in the city council in November
or that would take effect in January.
But it should be probably something to
look at at least after the election to
get going
because I think right now I think most
of the ones that voted against it are
still on the council.
But yeah, that's a good point.
Yeah, I mean I I think we just keep it
on the watch list and
I mean if anything new comes of it in
the next few months, I mean I think we
just keep going. But um I don't know if
anyone wants to
be tasked to do that. [laughter]
No. Okay.
Um
so I guess old business I don't think
there is any and any other I guess any
other business before we adjourn
chair. Um, I do have one.
I had a message from David Palasio's. I
I emailed him, but I haven't heard
anything back, but he said that
I believe that he did some brick work on
his chimney and that he was questioning
if he should come and give an update to
his to the board about the status of his
home. at this point in time
>> and we haven't heard anything in a long
time.
>> Yeah, I think an update would be great.
Okay, [laughter] I will try and get him
to come to the next meeting.
>> Chair, members of the board, I ran into
David at the front counter.
Believe it was Friday and said, "Hey
buddy,
it's
I said it was time for him to come to
the board to get an update." So, he's
expecting to fully do an update on where
he is, and he's very proud of the
chimney he's replaced that he had taken
down. So, the chimney that was there
that was once a brick chimney is now
back as a chimney. However, it's a
cinder block chimney that has replaced
it. So, but you are welcome to see that.
Um, but he's going to give an update on
where he is with the project and where
he's moving forward. So anyway, just
wanted to provide that
>> I guess question on that because I
thought we were pretty clear in the the
design of putting in the conditions of
putting elements back um of how they
were and a cinder block chimney is not
not appropriate.
So is that is that what we're going to
kind of speak on when it comes to
give us an update? I guess. Did you guys
know he was going to do a cinder block
chimney? Can
>> No.
>> I'll see if I can get a street view
without a keyboard.
>> No, whatever. I don't have a keyboard.
It's all right.
>> It's all right. Yeah, we can.
Um, I do have one more item that's
different than that that I would like to
bring up because uh GSA, a government
government agency is asking for us to
hurry it up, a federal government
agency, which surprising because they're
usually slower. So, I'm not too worried
about moving this forward. But um we've
had
some discussions regarding the Louisa
Swain Federal Building. Um who's not
aware of that? Does everyone know what
the Louisa Swain Federal Building is?
Okay. It's right literally just about
two blocks from here. Um it's a
four-story building um
that is um proposed for disposal by the
federal government. Um right now they
don't have any um people that they're
proposing to sell it to. Um they are
just looking to advertise and get get it
on board. Since it is identified as a
contributing structure, it's a
standalone contributing structure um or
national register property standalone.
um they had to go through the state
historic preservation office um to
identify potential mitigation measures
um for disposal of the property. The
mitigation uh measure that was
identified by the shipo was that an
agency that is capable of enforcing
uh elements of historic preservation
shall essentially um be granted an
easement
um and be the u basically a lean a
holder of that easement to ensure that
it remains. So, they've prepared a draft
preservation um easement or we they
prepared one. We modified it. Our
attorney's office did and they sent it
back to us and then I talked with John,
that's his name, Joseph, um with GSA cuz
he's chomping at the bit waiting to get
this done. Um but basically what they're
proposing
is for that building you know we have
this simple item the simple um easement
which
says
and I've asked for this baseline
documentation we have not received that
yet
um this is so they have that they've
created a report that um has this
documentation called the baseline
documentation that talks about the
exterior of the building, its historic
prominence, and also the lobby of the
building, which has some historical
significance, but we have not seen that
yet. Um, but basically, we would hold an
easement that prohibits any changes to
the exterior of the building or the
lobby
um of the building in perpetuity.
So, this is what was discussed at the
the state historic preservation office.
Um, I've reached out to them for some
further um clarifications and I've also
talked to Joseph with GSA regarding this
item because
my worst fear, not that I don't respect
the building, is
what happens if there is another
development opportunity that could
occur. Should we
Don't slap me when you hear this. Do we
want to paint ourselves into a corner
where we can absolutely never demolish
that building? Because right now, the
only time it can be demolished is
um by act of God or like fire, something
happens that warrants it to be um
demolished. So, that's really what I
wanted to chat with you all about is
what your take is on that.
Um, and if we wanted to
at least um where is it?
Let's see.
Long story short, it's if there is a
damage that's of no result from them, so
it would be like something like an act
of God, then it is the only time in
which it could be um demolished.
Um, we have the ability if we wish
to completely
link it to our demolition of
contributing structures review criteria,
which um, unfortunately we didn't
include in our staff report earlier, but
we probably should have. Um, but this
was in here.
>> Oh, it was
Oh, it was on the applicant submit
information. is if desired, we could put
in that agreement an alternative to
allow for demolition provided the
preservation board
evaluates these and finds these in the
affirmative. I'm not asking I'm just
asking you all for your feedback and I
understand if you all say heck no we
want to preserve it at all costs or um
I'm also open to understanding if you
all believe we should have an out that
would be based on this criteria
>> Patrick
>> just a question who owns a lean does it
does the city or does this board
>> chair U for you to board member Busos
will technically be the governing body
the city
>> the city
>> I guess my opinion I I don't know uh why
we would give a option for it to be
demolished because I think that sets up
for anyone to find a way to demolish it.
So I guess in my opinion, unless someone
convinces me otherwise, I I wouldn't
have provision for demolition.
>> Go ahead, Patrick. [laughter]
>> I feel exact opposite. I I just I've
seen so many so many instances where you
know a loophole is created and it gives
I don't know unfortunately a scrupulous
undevelop developer or you know somebody
an opportunity to demolish the building
and you know it it's gone forever and
and you can't
>> Yeah. No. So you agree that's we're
saying the same thing.
>> We're saying the same thing. I agree. We
agree. We don't want I don't want anyone
to demolish it ever.
>> Okay.
>> I don't want No, I do not want
>> Okay. I'm I'm with you, Amber. My
apologies. All right. I I don't want any
out.
>> We only We only disagreed on one thing
on this meeting. So, we're increasing on
this one,
[laughter]
but because I exactly what you said,
every someone will find a way to Yep. I
guess any any other opinions?
>> Yes, they'll just sell it to the city
and that I'm just kidding.
Too soon.
>> Chair members,
>> Charles, you are crazy for trying to
give us an out.
>> I I just I wanted to be fair. I I
believe that the conversation may come
up um at the governing body and I wanted
to fully vet the idea to the historic
preservation board to let them know
where that that is at. Um, but this is
the building itself. Um, I believe I
don't know who knows more about it, but
if I recall that this was originally a
three-story building and then they they
popped the top essentially at one time,
but you have this side that's facing uh
Kerry and then you have this is the uh
front of the building that's facing 21st
Street. Um, I have not been in the
lobby, but I've been uh put in touch
with the building um maintenance group.
Um, so I can have a limited tour, like a
tour setup where we could look at this
building. Um, if any wants to to be kind
of on a subcommittee and look at this,
I'd be more than happy to do that.
>> I I would like to be on that. I think
that I I would like to see what the
lobby is since it's something we're
including in the easement that we're
trying to protect. I want to know what
what it is.
>> Perfect.
>> Charles, just curious is did did Joseph
bring this issue up or is this something
that you're just contemplating that you
you just want our opinion on? Because I
I don't know. I I just
will they accept, you know, uh uh
leaving it
externally and the lobby in perpetuity.
Do you have any sense of that,
>> chair, members of the board? Um, this
was me just looking trying to look in
the crystal ball as to what questions
could I anticipate at the governing body
as we move forward. I was pretty
confident I understood what the historic
preservation board would want. I wanted
to make sure that I understood all
angles of everything. Um, after talking
with Joseph about two weeks ago, I
wanted to double check if it was
acceptable to have that provision in
there in case it came up. Um, I wholly
intend to present it based on the
Historic Preservation Board's
recommendation, which would be to
preserve the lobby and the exterior.
um if there is a um proposed change to
the easement document that would allow
for the demolition subject to those
criteria. Um I believe not only would I
need um to run that by you all just to
inform you all but I believe I do have
to run it by the state historic
preservation office because they were
the ones who identified the level of
mitigation in this specific case.
So, I've never been in this building.
Um, I don't know if anyone here has.
>> Uh, I got my social security card there
in 1964. Back when you Right. Now, you
have
>> back when you were born. Right.
>> No. Uh, you didn't have to uh put the
social security numbers on your income
tax until recently. Before that, and if
you I had to get one to get a checking
account, so I had to have a social
security number to give the bank. But
prior to that, you didn't need a a
number until, like I said, until you
actually did something financial. But
then they I guess people were claiming
they had like 300 kids on their tax
forms and uh [laughter]
with so they started making them to put
an actual number on there so they could
trace you from uh birth to death.
But they also had the IRS in there. And
my mom got audited full federal IRS
audits five years in a row after my even
though my parents were divorced and my
dad got convicted of felony tax evasion
and they went after her to see what what
was going on.
Well, it gets it's gets four 2.8 stars
um
based on uh four reviews.
I mean I I did see that even the
pyramids had bad reviews. So I mean it's
>> so chair. Okay. Um thank you for the
feedback. What I will do is
um we'll move forward with the easement
agreement. With that in mind, um I will
forward out a final copy to you all for
comment. We have one pretty darn close.
I'm still waiting on information from
Joseph. Um because one thing I wanted to
um include is that baseline report. No
matter how long it is, I think it's
probably 60 pages or something like
that. I want that to be an exhibit to
this easement that is recorded with the
property and at the uh the real estate
records group because right now as it's
proposed in the agreement, we're just
told to hold on to it at the city. And
I've seen what that looks like 30, 40,
50 years later. it doesn't look pretty.
So, I want to make sure we have someone
who really is a professional holding on
to things hold on to that as well.
>> Thank you.
>> Guess any other comments on that?
>> Any other business?
>> Chair, I guess could I get a motion just
affirming
>> what your your desire is?
>> Sure. Does someone want to make a motion
to
>> I I move that um char we authorize
Charles to negotiate with the GSA on the
uh easement for uh it's the what is it
Charles the Nelly
>> the Louisa Swain federal building on
21st
>> Louis
>> Louisa
>> Louisa Swain building um to uh advocate
for um No changes to the exterior or the
lobby in perpetuity.
>> That makes it.
>> That was a great motion. Thank you.
>> I'll second. I'll second.
>> Okay. Motion's been seconded. All in
favor say I.
>> I.
>> Any opposed? Same sign. Nope. Okay.
Motion passes.
>> Great. Thank you. That's all I had.
>> All right. Any other business? No. Okay.
I'm gonna I like doing this. We are
adjourned.